Register of the Elie Abel Papers, 1941-1978
Hoover Institution Archives
Elie Abel Papers,
1941-1978
84035
Abel, Elie
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (3.75 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, radio and television broadcast transcripts, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to world politics and to the press. Includes photocopies of drafts of and correspondence relating to the book by E. Abel, The Missile Crisis (1966). Also includes drafts of the book by E. Abel and W. Averell Harriman, Special Envoy to Churchill and Stalin, 1941-1946 (1975); letters and memoranda by Harriman; and photocopies of wartime dispatches to Harriman, all used in writing the book.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Journalism--United States.; World politics--1945-; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; Journalists.; Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962.; Cuba.
Biographical Note
1920, Oct. 17 Born, Montreal, Quebec, Canada
1941 Reporter, Windsor (Ontario) Star
1945-1946 Assistant City Editor, Montreal Gazette
1946-1947 Foreign Correspondent, North American Newspaper Alliance, Berlin, Germany
1947-1949 United Nations Correspondent, Overseas News Agency
1949-1959 Washington Correspondent and Foreign Correspondent, New York Times
1959-1961 Washington Bureau Chief, Detroit News
1965-1967 London Bureau Chief, NBC
1966 Author, The Missile Crisis
1967-1969 Diplomatic Correspondent, NBC News, Washington
1969-1979 Godfrey Lowell Cabot Professor, Columbia University, N.Y.C.
Dean, Graduate School of Journalism, Columbia University, N.Y.C.
1971 Author (with Marvin Kalb), Roots of Involvement: The U.S. in Asia, 1784-1971
1975 Author (with Averell Harriman), Special Envoy to Churchill and Stalin, 1941-1946
1979- Harry and Norman Chandler Professor, Stanford University, California
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1955-1977 (Box Box 1)
  Clippings and miscellany relating to the life of Elie Abel, arranged alphabetically by form.
  - Clippings, 1955-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Inventory and appraisal of Abel manuscript materials and correspondence, 1969 (Folder 2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1952-1978 (Box Boxes 1-4)
  Drafts and printed copies of books, articles, speeches, lectures, and book reviews by Elie Abel, with correspondence, notes, research materials and reviews relating to them, arranged chronologically by date of publication or writing.
  - General. Clippings, photocopies of others' writings, handwritten notes, most likely used in the drafting of speeches. Topics restricted to freedom of speech, academia (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Draft for article or speech, n.d. Relates to Robert McNamara. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - Notes for article or speech, n.d. Relates to John Foster Dulles background session, Geneva, November 2, 1955. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Speech, n.d. Relates to postwar Britain, and Common Market. Typescript. Fragment? (Folder 6)
  - Speeches, n.d. Typescript and handwritten notes on index cards. Fragments? (Folder 7)
  - Valparaiso Law Day Speech, n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Tank Output Lags 6 Months; 2 New Types 'Unacceptable', New York Times, January 6, 1952. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - Defective Tanks Pile Up in Depots, New York Times, January 7, 1952. Printed copy (Folder 10)
  - Portrait of 'Decontrol Charlie' Wilson, New York Times Magazine, December 14, 1952. Printed copy (Folder 11)
  - U.S. Short of Artillery Shells To Sustain Big Korea Drive, New York Times, February 21, 1953. Printed copy (Folder 12)
  - Army Overcoming Dearth of Shells, New York Times, February 22, 1953. Printed copy (Folder 13)
  - U.N. Still Too Short of Shells to Start Korea Drive, Detroit Free Press, February 22, 1953. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - What Can We Expect From the Next Summit Conference?, speech, The Economic Club of Detroit, November 16, 1959. Typescript. Includes printed copy of Detroit News announcement, review of speech and letter to editor, November 16, 17, 1959. Includes program (Folder 15)
  - Speech, Windsor Rotary Club, January 8, 1960. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - World at the Summit, Detroit News, May 15, 1960. Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - Kennedy After 8 Months is Tempered by Adversity, Detroit News?, 1961? Printed copy. Includes telex copy, September 19, 1961; correspondence with Muller, C., 1961? (Folder 18)
  - Review of Milovan Djilas, Montenegro, Reporter, November 7, 1963. Printed copy (Folder 19)
  - The Missile Crisis, 1966
    - General. Handwritten and typewritten notes. Printed matter by others. Notes of W. Averell Harriman and Eugene McCarthy talk (Folder 20)
    - Abel vs ABC et al.
      - Clippings, 1974-1975 (Folder 21)
      - Correspondence, 1974-1978
        - Abel
          - Covington & Burling, 1976 (Folder 22)
          - Hall, Dickler, Lawler, Kent & Howley, 1975-1978. Includes photocopy of opinion for Meeropol vs Nizer et al.; J.B. Lippincott Co. royalty statements 1966-1972 (Folder 23)
        - Other, arranged by sender
          - Paul R. Reynolds, Inc., 1974-1975 (Folder 24)
          - Hall, Dickler, Lawler, Kent & Howley, 1976 (Folder 25)
    - Clippings, 1966-1968 (Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1977
      - Paul R. Reynolds, Inc., 1968, 1977. Includes photocopy of copyright registration (Folder 27)
      - Wisch, Steve, 1975 (Folder 28)
    - Reviews and promotional material, 1966
      - English. Printed copies (Folder 29)
      - French. Printed copy (Folder 30)
      - German. Printed copy (Folder 31)
  - The Press at Bay, 1970, Guild Memorial Lecture, University of Minnesota, October 15, 1970. Typescript. Includes photocopy with annotations (Folder 32)
  - Speech, University of Deleware, January 12, 1971. Letter of thanks, and review only (Folder 33)
  - Ferris Lecture, Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs, Princeton University, April 6, 1971. Typescript. Fragment? (Folder 34)
  - Roots of Involvement: The U.S. in Asia, 1784-1971, 1971
    - Clipping, n.d. (Folder 35)
    - Correspondence. W.W. Norton & Co. Inc., 1976. In form of royalty statement for 1975-1976 (Folder 36)
    - Reviews, 1971-1972 (Folder 37)
  - Speech, The National Association of FM Broadcasters in Chicago, April 8, 1972. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - Special Envoy to Churchill and Stalin, 1975 (Box 2)
    - General
      - Notes for speech on the writing of Special Envoy, Corcoran Gallery, May 10, 1976 (Folder 1)
      - Author resume, book proposals, book outline, photo captions, Random House author's questionnaire, draft of Random House announcement of Special Envoy (Folder 2)
      - Notes, typewritten and handwritten (Folder 3)
      - Research materials not to be found in Harriman correspondence below: photocopies of addresses, classified telegrams, correspondence, recollections, excerpts from books, most of which relevant to Harriman's tenure of 1941-1945 (Folder 4)
      - Partial drafts of Chapters II, VIII, XIII, XXI. Typescript (Folder 5)
      - Index, draft and master (Folder 6)
      - Setting copy (Folder 7-9)
      - Setting copy (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Clippings, 1972-1976 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Abel
        - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 4)
        - Abrahamsen, David, 1975 (Folder 5)
        - Balk, Albert, 1975 (Folder 6)
        - Berger, Marilyn, 1974 (Folder 7)
        - Brennan, Pat, 1975 (Folder 8)
        - Bundy, McGeorge, 1976 (Folder 9)
        - Bernays, Edward L., 1973 (Folder 10)
        - Clurman, Richard M., 1975 (Folder 11)
        - Cook, Don, 1976 (Folder 12)
        - Erickson, Michael E., 1977 (Folder 13)
        - Forrestal, Michael V., 1974, 1975. Includes photocopy of correspondence with Dillon, Clarence, 1974 (Folder 14)
        - Graff, Henry F., 1975 (Folder 15)
        - Harriman, W. Averell, 1972-1977. These are largely of Harriman recollections and remarks on chapters written. Several contain research materials and photocopies of others' correspondence
          - n.d. Includes photocopy of printed book review, and Harriman remarks on Chapters I, II (Folder 16)
          - 1972. Includes agreement signed by Abel and Harriman with conditions and stipulations of enterprise (Folder 17)
          - 1973 (Folder 18)
          - 1974. Includes correspondence with Berger, Samuel D. (includes photocopy of Berger, Samuel D. and Kerr, Alexander C., Dock Labour Situation in British Ports, May 1942); Manning, Robert (Folder 19)
          - 1975. Includes correspondence with Bruce, David; The Century Association, n.d.; Galbraith, John Kenneth; Harriman, Edward Henry, 1909; Harriman, Mary. n.d.; Knopf, Alfred A.; Korbonski, Stefan; Meiklejohn, Robert P., (includes selected diary entries of 1945); McCloy, John J.; TV Guide. Includes photocopy of Shvernik tribute to President Roosevelt at opening of Supreme Soviet, 1945; photocopies of newspaper clippings of Harriman as poloist, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - 1976. Includes correspondence with Bullard, Julian; Butterton, Meredith L.; Curley, Walter J. P.; Eaker, Ira C. (includes photocopy of Eaker's review); Fedynskyj, Jurij; Hughes-Onslow, Neil; Kahn, Irving; Paul R. Reynolds, Inc., 1977 (includes copy of contract for German publication); Random House; Sherwin, Martin J.; Sinsheimer, Bernard; Van Devander, Charles, 1977; Ward, Geoffrey (includes galley of Mee, Charles L., Jr., The Cold War). Includes photocopies of proposed contract for British publication rights; translation of review in Literaturnaya Gazeta, Jan. 21, 1976; photocopy of review in The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1976 (Folder 2)
          - 1977. Includes correspondence with Van Devander, Charles (Folder 3)
        - Holbrooke, Richard, 1975 (Folder 4)
        - Kalb, Marvin, 1975 (Folder 5)
        - Kempner, Marshall S., 1976 (Folder 6)
        - Kendall, David W., 1976 (Folder 7)
        - Knopf, Alfred A., 1975 (Folder 8)
        - Lasky, Melvin J., 1976 (Folder 9)
        - Lowenfeld, Andreas F., 1976 (Folder 10)
        - Mahoney, Florence, 1975 (Folder 11)
        - Manning, Robert, 1972-1974 (Folder 12)
        - Meier, Charles S., 1972-1975. Includes memorandum to participants in Harriman Seminar, 1969 (Folder 13)
        - Meiklejohn, Robert P., 1975 (Folder 14)
        - Murphy, Robert D., 1975 (Folder 15)
        - Nicoll, Courtlandt, 1977. Includes copy of UPI report on interview with Harriman (Folder 16)
        - Paul R. Reynolds, Inc., 1973-1978. Includes photocopy of both review and quote from Special Envoy appearing in USA Economics, Politics, Ideology, May 1976 (Folder 17)
        - Petrow, R., 1975 (Folder 18)
        - Random House, Inc., 1973-1977. Includes correspondence with Eisenhower, John L. D., 1975; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1975; Lovett, Robert, 1975?; Mortimer, Kathleen (Harriman), 1975; Ridgway, M. B., 1975; Silkenat, James R., 1976 (includes photocopy of Silkenat review); Sulzberger, C.L., 1975; White, Theodore H., 1975. Includes sample layouts for title page, text, advertisement, quote from reviewer David Bruce, and drafts for author resumes (Folder 19)
        - Rossman, Malcolm, 1976 (Folder 20)
        - Rusk, Dean, 1975 (Folder 21)
        - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 1976 (Folder 22)
        - Shore, Ben, 1975 (Folder 23)
        - Sulzberger, C. L., 1975 (Folder 24)
        - Verlag Fritz Molden, 1976 (Folder 25)
        - Ward, Geoffrey C., 1977 (Folder 26)
        - Westfeldt, A., 1976 (Folder 27)
        - Williams, Franklin H., 1977 (Folder 28)
        - Zaremba, Andrew, 1975 (Folder 29)
      - Other, arranged by sender
        - Bundy, McGeorge, 1975 (Folder 30)
        - Buttenweiser, Benjamin J., 1973 (Folder 31)
        - Kaiser, Robert and Hannah, n.d. (Folder 32)
        - Rusk, Dean, 1973 (Folder 33)
        - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 1973 (Folder 34)
    - Reviews and promotional material, 1972-1977
      - English. Printed copies (Folder 35)
      - Portuguese. Printed copy (Folder 36)
      - Russian. Printed copy (Folder 37)
- Incremental Materials (Box 5-9)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu